Guide to the University Counseling Center records, 1963-1989 RG0049
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
University Counseling Center records
1963-2003
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. University Counseling Center
RG0049
6.75 Linear Feet
Collection includes annual reports, research papers, video tapes, brochures, and slides.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 and 2 are closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from University Counseling Center.
Historical Note
Established in 1954, the University Counseling Center at The George Washington University (GW) services to help students resolve personal, social, career, and study problems that can interfere with their academic progress and success. Services include individual counseling, crisis intervention, group counseling, and workshops on topics such as time management, study skills, procrastination prevention, family and relationship issues, choosing a career, stress management, conflict management, and self-esteem/self-development.
The Center offers consultation and training programs for student, faculty, and staff groups. Career counseling and referral services are available to GW students, faculty, staff, alumni, and individuals from the greater Washington community. The Center provides pamphlets, books, and tapes through its self-help library. Students can apply for tutors through the Center's Peer Tutoring Service, which matches tutors with students requesting assistance for specific academic courses.
The Center began as the Testing and Counseling Center (1954-64), then became the Psychological Clinic (1965-1970), and the Counseling Center in 1971. Dr. E. Lakin Philips was its long-time director from 1963 to 1985. The Director of the Center reports to the Senior Vice President for Student and Academic Support Services.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include annual reports, research papers, video tapes of the annual "chalk-in," brochures, and slides shows (chalk-in, The George Washington University as an urban campus, art therapy). They range in date from 1963-89, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Director of the University Counseling Center.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Reports and papers; Papers, slides, and video tapes; and Office files.
Washington (D.C.); Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Counseling; Art therapy; Color slides; George Washington University
- Reports and papers, 1983-1988; RG0049 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  The series consists of annual reports and research papers. They range in date from 1983 to 1988.
  - The Development of an Instrument for Measuring Leadership in Behaviors in Therapy Groups, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Diane Depalma, Katheryn Gardner, Thomas Zastowny
  - The Development of a Scale to Measure Defensive Externality in both Success and Failure Conditions, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Maureen Kearney
  - Construction and VAlidation of a Scale to Measure Defensive Externality in Success Situations, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Maureen Kearny
  - Stress, Strain, and Burnout among Career Development Professionals, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Dea Forney and T. Thorne Wiggers
  - A Comparison of Motivation to Avoid Success in Males and Females, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biblio/Poetry Therapy as Expressive Arts Therapy, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    E. Lakin Phillips
  - Prescriptions for Systematic Change: Attrition from Psychotherapy with several Research Proposals, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - How every Aspect of Psychotherapy is Affected by the Attrition Curve, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Help-Seeking Behavior: A New Context for Psychotherapy Evaluation, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - From Single Clinic Service Delivery Systems to Interagency Treatment: Generalizations Based on the Poisson Attrition Curve, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Research on the Use of Art Therapy in a University Setting, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    E. Lakin Phillips, Sondra Geller, Marty Ireland
  - Annual Report, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Report, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Report, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Papers, slides, and video tapes, 1963-1989; RG0049 Series 2; 3 Linear feet
  The series consists of annual reports and papers, video tapes (chalk-in), brochures, and slides shows (chalk-in, The George Washington University (GW) as urban campus, GW art therapy). They range in date from 1963 to 1989.
  - Annual Report, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Academic Tapes, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Academic Tapes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brochures (undated, but before 1978) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brochures, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brochures, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bookmark, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brochures for Community Vocational Counseling Services, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brochures for Community Vocational Counseling Services, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brochures for Community Vocational Counseling Services (undated, but between 1980 and 1987) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brochures for Community Vocational Counseling Services, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brochures for Community Vocational Counseling Services, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Fall), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Fall), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Fall), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Fall), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Fall), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Fall), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered - cover only (Fall), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Fall), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Spring), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Announcements/catalogs of groups offered (Fall), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Counseling Center Fees for Service: One System and Its Implications, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Publicity Materials (newspaper clippings, etc.), 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - George Washington University Volunteer Hotline, a Descriptive Study (Herman, Davis, Phillips), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Developing an Art Therapy Program in a University Counseling Center (Geller, DePalma, Daw), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Clinical and Personal Experiences with Loss Support Groups (Medvene, DePalma, and Houshi), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Construction and Validation of a Scale to Measure Defensive Externality in Success Situations (Kearney), undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Characteristics of Bulimics Seeking Psychotherapy Treatment (Kearney), undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Burnout: Targets for Prevention (Wiggers), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - The Use of Self-help Books in Counseling and Psychotherapy (Stern, Marx, Gyorky, Royalty), undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Use of Psychologist's Drawings in the Understanding of Supervisory Transference (Ireland, Weissman, and Wiggers), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Importance of the Masculinity Scale of the BEM Sex-Role Inventory in Predicting Locus of Control (Kearney), undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - The Group Leader Behavior Instrument (DePalma, Gardner, and Zastowny), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Attrition: Focus on the Intake and First Therapy Interviews (Phillips and Fagan), undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - There are Ways to Fight College Anxiety and Stress (Robbins and Tanck), undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - When Words are Not Enough: Art Therapy for College Students (DePalma and Wiggers), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Burnout is not Necessary: Prevention and Recovery (Wiggers, Forney and Wallace-Schutman), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Toward a Comprehensive Assessment of Leadership Behaviors in Groups (Gardner, DePalma, Zastowny), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - The Environment and the Student in Counseling Psychology: Does the Research Training Environment Influence Graduate Students' Attitudes Toward Research? (Royalty, Gelso, Mallinckrodt, and Garrett), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - "Artbreak": Innovation in Student Life Programming (Geller, Kwapien, Phillips, Wiggers, Jordan, and Marcellino), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - The Research Training of Counseling Psychologists: What the Professionals Say (Royalty, and Raising), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Linking University Departments to Promote Treatment of Bulimia (Kearney), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - College Students' Attitudes Toward Wellness (Archer, Probert, and Gage), undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Attributions of Defensive and Congruent Internals/Externals in Success and Failure Conditions (Kearney), undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Correlates of Scholarly Productivity Among Counseling Psychologists (Royalty and Magoon), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Confidentiality in Group Psychotherapy (Kearney), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - SLIDE SHOW: GWU as urban campus, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - SLIDE SHOW: Chalk-In, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - SLIDE SHOW: Expressive Arts in Mental Health Festival, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - SLIDE SHOW: Early GW Art Therapy Outreach. This was used for PR "in house" and "out", undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - VIDEOTAPE: Exam Treat, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - VIDEOTAPE: Chalk-In, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - VIDEOTAPE: Chalk-In (2 tapes), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - VIDEOTAPE: Chalk-In, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Office files, 1980-1986; RG0049 Series 3; .25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  The series contains brocheres, annual reports, and flyers from the Counseling Center. They range in date from 1980-1986.
  - Counseling Center, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Counseling Center Annual Report, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Counseling Center - Brochures, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Counseling Center photographs, 1980-2003; RG0049 Series 4; 3 Linear Feet Two boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Contains photograph albums and organized loose photographs of GW University Counseling Center staff, student employees, and events such as the annual Chalk In.
  - Photographs, 1980-2003 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1980-2003 (Box 2)